John Clement Fitzpatrick Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
John Clement Fitzpatrick Papers 1927-1941
MSS20750
Fitzpatrick, John Clement, 1876-1940
14,000 items
23 containers plus 9 oversize
9.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Archivist, librarian, historian, and editor. Chiefly correspondence relating to The Writings of George Washington edited by Fitzpatrick, together with card files indexing the work, drafts of speeches and of a study of Virginia colonial governors, and other papers and reference files.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951--Correspondence.; Anderson, Maxwell, 1888-1959--Correspondence.; Ball, George A. (George Alexander), 1862-1955--Correspondence.; Bloom, Sol, 1870-1949--Correspondence.; Boyd, Julian P. (Julian Parks), 1903-1980--Correspondence.; Cook, Roy Bird, 1886-1961--Correspondence.; Fitzpatrick, John Clement, 1876-1940, The writings of George Washington from the original manuscript sources, 1745-1799. 1931-1944.; Fitzpatrick, John Clement, 1876-1940.; Gaines, Francis Pendleton, 1892-1963--Correspondence.; Garrison, Curtis Wiswell, 1901-1979--Correspondence.; Gottschalk, Louis F. (Louis Ferdinand), 1869-1934--Correspondence.; Grant, U. S. (Ulysses S.), 1881-1968--Correspondence.; Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943--Correspondence.; Henderson, Archibald, 1877-1963--Correspondence.; Hughes, Rupert, 1872-1956--Correspondence.; Jameson, J. Franklin (John Franklin), 1859-1937--Correspondence.; Lear, Tobias, 1762-1816.; Matteson, David Maydole, 1871-1949--Correspondence.; Morison, Samuel Eliot, 1887-1976--Correspondence.; Page, Elwin L. (Elwin Lawrence), 1876-1974--Correspondence.; Paltsits, Victor Hugo, 1867-1952--Correspondence.; Penniman, Josiah Harmar, 1868-1941--Correspondence.; Richardson, William H., 1864-1937--Correspondence.; Robertson, James Alexander, 1873-1939--Correspondence.; Spofford, Ernest--Correspondence.; Swem, E. G. (Earl Gregg), 1870-1965--Correspondence.; Wall, Alexander J. (Alexander James), 1884-1944--Correspondence.; Wall, Charles Cecil--Correspondence.; Washington family.; Washington, George, 1732-1799--Family.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.; Weinberger, Bernhard Wolf, 1885-1960--Correspondence.; Woodhouse, Henry, 1884- --Correspondence.
Organizations
George Washington Bicentennial Commission (U.S.); Library of Congress--Officials and employees.; Military Order of the Purple Heart.; United States. Constitution.
Subjects
Dwellings--Virginia.; Governors--Virginia.; Medals, Military and naval--United States.; Plantations--Virginia.
Places
Mount Vernon (Va.: Estate); New Jersey--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; Virginia--Politics and government--To 1775.
Occupations
Archivists.; Editors.; Historians.; Librarians.
Provenance
The papers of John Clement Fitzpatrick, archivist, librarian, historian, and editor, were given to the Library of Congress by Fitzpatrick's sister, Katherine F. Rodgers, in 1940. An addition was transferred from the Library of Congress Archives to the Manuscript Division in 1988.
Additional Guides
An author and subject card index to Fitzpatrick's general correspondence prepared by Katherine Claggett, Fitzpatrick's secretary, is available in the Manuscript Division Reading Room.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of John Clement Fitzpatrick are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1876, Aug. 10 Born, Washington, D.C.
1894 Graduated,Washington High School, Washington, D.C.
1897 Joined staff of Library of Congress and began work in the Manuscript Division
1913 Published Notes on the Care, Cataloguing and Arranging of Manuscripts. Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office
1918 Edited The Autobiography of Martin Van Buren (issued as vol. 2 of 1918 Annual Report of the American Association. Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1920)
1924 Published The Spirit of the Revolution: New Light from Some of the Original Sources of American History. Boston and New York: Houghton Mifflin Co.
1926 Awarded honorary degree from George Washington University, Washington, D.C.
1927 Published George Washington, Colonial Traveller, 1732-1799. Indianapolis: Bobbs-Merrill Co. Promoted to acting chief, Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
1928 Resigned from Library of Congress and assumed editorship for the George Washington Bicentennial Commission of the Writings of George Washington, 39 vols.
1928 1929 President, American Catholic Historical Association
1929 Published The George Washington Scandals, Washington Society of Alexandria, bulletin no. 1
1931 Published Washington as a Religious Man. Washington, D.C.: George Washington Bicentennial Commission
1939 Published Some Historic Houses, Their Builders and Their Plans. New York: The Macmillan Co.
1940, Feb. 10 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of John Clement Fitzpatrick (1876-1940) comprise four series spanning 1927-1940: General Correspondence, Correspondence with Sol Bloom, Miscellany, and Oversize. The bulk of the papers consists of correspondence dating between 1927 and 1941 centering on Fitzpatrick's service as editor of The Writings of George Washington from the Original Manuscript Sources, 1745-1799, prepared under the direction of the George Washington Bicentennial Commission. Included are letters concerning the location of original Washington documents to be published in the volumes and correspondence with the Government Printing Office relating to the printing of these volumes.
Because Fitzpatrick was widely regarded as an authority on George Washington, much of the General Correspondence series concerns inquiries the editor received about Washington. The nationwide observance of the bicentennial of Washington's birth stimulated interest in every conceivable aspect of Washington's personal and public life. Fitzpatrick's replies to these wide-ranging questions are a valuable source of information on Washington. Various letters concern Washington's appearance and his dental problems, dentures, and dentist. There is also correspondence regarding the president's birthday, birthplace, death, burial, grave, and life mask, as well as other questions about his education and his ideas on education, his library, bookplate, sword, and the coat of arms and genealogy of the Washington family. Also included is a reply concerning a portrait of Mary Ball Washington, George Washington's mother, and considerable material on various portraits of Washington and Jean Antoine Houdon's bust of the president. Additionally, Fitzpatrick received many inquiries about the Washington "scandals," which he had attempted to refute in his pamphlet published in 1929. Washington's acts of charity, his religion and the so-called Washington's prayer, and his order against profanity are among other topics covered.
Fitzpatrick also received letters inquiring about Washington's surveys, travels, and writings, including among the latter his diaries, journals, account books, farewell address to the army, presidential farewell address, and both inaugural addresses. There is material relating to Mount Vernon, to Washington's marriage, including the date, place, and officiating minister, and to Washington's Masonic activities. There is also material relating to the origin of the Purple Heart award, correspondence about the papers of Washington's aide and friend, Tobias Lear, and answers to queries regarding the Declaration of Independence.
Sol Bloom, United States representative from New York, was vice chairman of the Washington Bicentennial Commission. There are letters to and from him in the General Correspondence series and also a separate series of his correspondence in connection with the commission. Bloom was interested in the observance of the sesquicentennial of the Constitution, and his correspondence contains a file, 1934-1938, concerning this project. William H. Richardson of New Jersey is also heavily represented in Fitzpatrick's General Correspondence. Richardson wrote extensively about the history of New Jersey during the American Revolution, Washington's activities in New Jersey, and the "Flying Camp." Also included in the collection is a file of mimeographed and printed matter that was sent to Fitzpatrick by Richardson.
Among the items in the Miscellany are photostats of letters of most signers of the Constitution, drafts of and notes for speeches by Fitzpatrick, proofs of the index and illustrative material for Writings of George Washington, plates of illustrations for Fitzpatrick's Aides and Secretaries to Gen. George Washington, transcripts, notes and drafts relating to a study of Virginia colonial governors, miscellaneous newspaper clippings, and Oversize photostats of amendments and proposed amendments to the Constitution.
In 1988 three card files maintained by Fitzpatrick were added to the collection. One file contains addresses of acquaintances, reference librarians, historical societies, book shops, publishers and editors, heads of history department, and historians. The second file is Fitzpatrick's working card index to his Writings of George Washington, and the third is a record of the material that he sent to the Government Printing Office for the publication of the Writings.
Correspondents in the General Correspondence series include Randolph Greenfield Adams, Maxwell Anderson, George A. Ball, Sol Bloom, Julian P. Boyd, Roy Bird Cook, Francis Pendleton Gaines, Curtis Wiswell Garrison, Louis F. Gottschalk, U. S. Grant (1881-1968), Alfred Bushnell Hart, Archibald Henderson, Rupert Hughes, J. Franklin Jameson, David Maydole Matteson, Samuel Eliot Morison, Elwin L. Page, Victor Hugo Paltsits, Josiah Harmar Penniman, William H. Richardson, James Alexander Robertson, Ernest Spofford, E. G. Swem, Alexander J. Wall, Charles Cecil Wall, Bernard Wolf Weinberger, and Henry Woodhouse.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
General Correspondence, 1927-1940
Correspondence with Sol Bloom, 1930-1941
Miscellany
Oversize
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1927-1940 (Box 1-14)
  Letters received and sent relating mainly to Writings of George Washington and questions and answers relating to all aspects of Washington's public and private life.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1927-1929, including two letters of Winfield S. Hancock, 1866, 1873 (Box 1)
  - 1930 (Box 2)
    - Jan.-Aug. (Box 2)
    - Sept.-Dec. (Box 3)
  - 1931 (Box 4)
    - Jan.-June (Box 4)
    - July-Dec. (Box 5)
  - 1932 (Box 6)
    - Jan.- Apr. (Box 6)
    - May-Dec. (Box 7)
  - 1933 (Box 8)
  - 1934 (Box 9)
  - 1935 (Box 10)
  - 1936 (Box 11)
  - 1937 (Box 12)
  - 1938 (Box 13)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 14)
- Correspondence with Sol Bloom, 1930-1941 (Box 15-16)
  Correspondence with Bloom on general topics and concerning the sesquicentennial of the Constitution.
  - General, 1930-1941 (Box 15)
  - U. S. Constitution, sesquincentinial, 1934-1938 (Box 16)
- Miscellany (Box 17-24)
  Correspondence, draft writings, articles, notes, meeting minutes, printed matter, newspaper clippings, photostats, and miscellaneous material relating to New Jersey in the American revolution and to other Revolutionary War era topics, and to Writings of George Washington and other works by Fitzpatrick and others.
  Arranged by topic.
  - Material from William H. Richardson, including article on the "Flying Camp," mimeographed and printed matter, and newspaper clippings relating to the revolution in New Jersey. (Box 17)
  - Printer's proofs of index to Writings of George Washington (Box 18)
  - Illustrative material for Writings of George Washington (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, minutes, and miscellaneous notes relating to the advisory committee on the Writings of George Washington; copies of lists of questions and answers regarding Washington compiled for Sol Bloom; list of Washington letters in various institutions; photostatic copies of letters of the signers of the Constitution (incomplete); photostat of a portrait of Washington by Edward Savage; notes and miscellaneous matter from Katherine Claggett, secretary to Fitzpatrick as editor of the Writings of George Washington. (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous notes concerning Washington; notes on Haym Salomon; text of two speeches; notes on Theodore Roosevelt; engravings of portraits of Washington; copies of acts of Congress and other printed matter concerning the Washington Bicentennial Commission; galley proof of autobiography of Jonathan Boucher; other miscellany (Box 21)
  - Transcripts, edited drafts, and notes relating to a study of Virginia's colonial governors; plates of illustrations for Fitzpatrick's Aides and Secretaries to Gen. George Washington (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings (Box 23)
  - Photostats of ammendments and proposed ammendments to the Constitution See Oversize (Box 23)
  - Card indexes See Oversize (Box 23)
- Oversize (Box OV 1-OV 9)
  Photostats of amendments and proposed amendments to the Constitution and card indexes
  Arranged and described according to the containers and folders from which the material was removed.
  - Photostats of amendments and proposed amendments to the Constitution, transferred from Sol Bloom's office (Container 23) (Box OV 1)
  - Card indexes (Container 23) (Box OV 2)
    - Address file (Box OV 2)
      - A-H (Box OV 2)
      - I-Z (Box OV 3)
    - Index to Writings of George Washington (Box OV 4)
      - A-Co (Box OV 4)
      - Cr-He (Box OV 5)
      - Hi-Ma (Box OV 6)
      - Me-Po (Box OV 7)
      - Pr-T (Box OV 8)
      - U-Z (Box OV 9)
    - Record of material sent to the Government Printing Office relating to Writings of George Washington (Box OV 9)